Guide to the Robert Ensko Inc. Records 1787-1798, 1908-1978 (bulk 1934-1970) MS 200
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Photographs and Pictorial Works, 1787, 1908-1971 (bulk 1950s-1960s); 12 Linear feet
  - Catalogues and other, circa 1927-1971 (Offsite-box 9)
    This box holds a variety of printed material. These include a few auction catalogues from Parke-Bernet (1946-65) and American Art Association/Anderson Galleries (1929-37); museum exhibition catalogues from Los Angeles County Museum, to which Ensko lent (1950), Metropolitan Museum of Art (1963-64), Minneapolis Institute of Arts (1956), Virginia Museum of Fine Arts (1960), and Wadsworth Atheneum (1945); museum and historical society booklets and reprints with articles on silver (1946-65); booklet and souvenir postcards about the Mabel Brady Garvan silver collection at Yale University Art Gallery (1960); and sales catalogues from Tuttle Silversmiths (1969) and Reed & Barton (1971), both firms represented in the correspondence and bills paid files of this collection. Other documents include: two books: "Plating and Finishing Guidebook" (1945) and "Early Ohio Taverns" by R.M. Knittle (1937); "Sterling Flatware Pattern Index, Revised Edition" (1941) issued by the Jewelers' Circular-Keystone; a manuscript list prepared by Lockwood Barr in 1943 of Kentucky silver and its makers (1790-1875); and two small booklets "17th and 18th Century American Silver" (1934) published by Robert Ensko Inc., likely as a primer for educating potential clients (one of the booklets includes a form of coat of arms for the company). Finally, the box holds a set of index cards with typed notes on various silversmiths; an enclosed paper slip says these relate to Stephen Ensko's 1927 book "American Silversmiths and Their Marks."
- Series III. Inventories and Financial Records, 1929-1971; 34 Linear feet
  The series includes various accounting and financial records for Robert Ensko Inc. These especially include records related to Ensko's inventory of silver objects, including invoices from silversmiths, engravers and other dealers to Ensko; index cards, stock purchase journals, photograph albums, and other forms of inventory records; and accounts payable ledgers. The series also includes accounting and bill payment records related to client/customer transactions and general business expenses. The earliest years of the incorporated firm are represented in the series with its corporate tax returns.
  The series is organized in three subseries:
  Subseries III.A. Bill Payment Files (circa 1934-1969)
  Subseries III.B. Stock Books & Other Inventories (1932-1978)
  Subseries III.C. Accounting Records (1929-1971)
  - Subseries III.A. Bill Payment Files, circa 1934-1969; 18.17 Linear feet
    This subseries includes the files of bills/invoices paid by Robert Ensko Inc. from about 1934 to the close of the business in 1970. These bills include both general business expenses and payments to dealers, silversmiths, and other firms for silver reproductions and antiques, as well as to engravers.
    Certain suppliers of silver objects appear frequently across the years, including Captain I.M. Harris & Co., I. Freeman & Son, Michael Feinberg Inc./Feinberg English Silver Inc., Ralph Hyman (London), H.D. Robbins & Co., Reed & Barton, L. Tobert (New York) and B. Tobert (London), and Tuttle Silver Co. Other dealers appear less frequently but still have a considerable presence at times including N. Bloom & Son, Williams Comyn & Sons Ltd., Currier & Roby Inc., Reginald Davis (London), Elgin Silversmith Company, International Silver Co., Victor Obler Company, J. Ortman, William B. Meyers Company (Newark, NJ), and Wakely & Wheeler (London), among others. Bills from two engravers stand out in their volume: William Carbine (from the 1930s until perhaps the mid-1950s) and H. Sigal Inc. (which appears on early invoices as Hillel Sigal).
    Although there is a substantial volume of bills from suppliers of silver objects, much of the bills paid files consist of general expenses, including those for shipping, photography, utilities, employee health benefits and other insurance, catering, office and display supplies, florists, various taxes, accounting services, legal matters, and the like.
    The subseries also includes some petty cash receipts, mostly from the late 1940s and into the 1950s, and cancelled checks, checkbook stubs, and bank statements for various years, especially from the 1950s.
    The subseries is arranged with bills paid files first, followed by the petty cash and banking records.
    The bills paid files retain their original order, which includes multiple sets of bills arranged alphabetically by vendor. The sets advance in rough chronological order from the 1930s to 1970. Invoices from the 1960s are loose in two boxes but in rough alphabetical order.
    The petty cash and bank statements/cancelled are in chronological order.
    - Bills Paid, circa 1934-1941 (Offsite-box 48)
      Includes three sets of invoices paid by Ensko: a) circa 1934-1936 (bulk, 1936), almost entirely product-related (no general business expenses); b) circa 1937-early 1940, with both product and general expenses, though this set appears incomplete (has only letters E-O); and c) circa late 1940-1941. Also, one folder of bills paid to engraver William Carbine (1937-1942), with some other invoices including those from engraver Hillel Sigal (circa 1934-1936).
    - Bills Paid (RESTRICTED), circa 1941-1945 (Offsite-box 49)
      RESTRICTED: These files require conservation vacuum treatment before they can be used. The box holds two sets of invoices paid by Ensko. Because of their condition, they were not closely inspected, but they appear to include all invoices (product and general business) for circa 1942 and invoices from Ensko's major product suppliers for circa 1941-1945.
    - Bills Paid, circa 1942-1946 (Offsite-box 50)
      There are two sets of bills in this box: circa 1943-45 and late 1945-46, with a few invoices back to 1942. The 1943-45 set appears to have few of the major suppliers and these are likely in the preceding box.
    - Bills Paid, 1946-1952 (Offsite-box 51)
      Includes a few invoices from 1946-1950, especially from engravers William Carbine. Bulk of box are invoices from circa 1951-1952, A-R.
    - Bills Paid, 1951-1954 (Offsite-box 52)
      Includes 1951-1952, S-Z; 1953-1954, A-Q
    - Bills Paid, 1953-1960 (Offsite-box 53)
      Includes 1953-1954, R-Z; 1955-1960, A-B and William Carbine, 1953-1956.
    - Bills Paid, 1955-1960 (Offsite-box 54)
      Includes 1955-1960, C-E and F (only I. Freeman & Sons)
    - Bills Paid, 1955-1960 (Offsite-box 55)
      Includes 1955-1960, F (excluding I. Freeman)-H (including Captain Harris)
    - Bills Paid, 1955-1960 (Offsite-box 56)
      Includes 1955-1960, I-R (excluding H.D. Robbins)
    - Bills Paid, 1955-1960 (Offsite-box 57)
      Includes 1955-1960, R (only H.D. Robbins)-T. This set includes invoices from engraver H. Sigel.
    - Bills Paid, 1955-1960 (Offsite-box 58)
      Includes 1955-1960, U-Z.
    - Shipping-related payments, 1959-1970 (Offsite-box 58)
      Includes: Railway Express Agency prepaid shipper's forms (1959-60), Postal Service declarations of value of registered mail for shipped items (1965, 1969-70), and UPS pick-up records (1970).
    - Bills Paid, circa 1961-1969 (Offsite-box 26)
      This box and the next holds loose invoices and statements sent by vendors to Ensko for payment. Roughly alphabetical order by vendor. Includes both general business expenses and those related to core business (engravers, dealers of silver). This box holds letters A-H, including: Philip Aaron (engraver), Captain I.M. Harris & Co, J. Freeman & Son Inc., Michael Feinberg Inc., Elgin Silversmith Co., Williams Comyn & Sons Ltd., and N. Bloom & Son Ltd.
    - Bills Paid, circa 1961-1969 (Offsite-box 27)
      Includes vendors H-U with, among others: Jack Lamberti Inc., Reed & Barton, H. Sigal Inc (engravers), Thomas Silversmith Inc., and Wakely & Wheeler (London).
    - Miscellaneous, 1960-1970 (Offsite-box 42)
      Generally appears to include various pending transactions from around 1969-70, that is just after the death of Stephen G.C. Ensko. Includes invoices, A-Z (1969-70) from, among others I. Freeman & Son, H. Sigal Inc., and Wakely & Wheeler; orders from New York Racing Association and related invoices to Ensko (1970); letters regarding resolutions of outstanding credits to clients; and pending matters at Ensko's death, 1960-70.
    - Petty cash, cancelled checks, bank statements, 1940, 1947-1950 (Offsite-box 43)
      Cancelled checks (1940); petty cash receipts (1947, 1949, 1950); bank statements with cancelled checks (1950)
    - Petty cash receipts, 1952-1954 (Offsite-box 44)
    - Petty cash receipts, cancelled checks, bank statements, 1955, 1957-1958 (Offsite-box 45)
      Petty cash receipts for January-June 1955 and for 1957; none for the later months of 1955 and 1956. Bank statements with cancelled checks for 1957 and January-June 1958 (see next box for continuation)
    - Petty cash receipts, cancelled checks, bank statements, 1958-1959 (Offsite-box 46)
      Petty cash receipts for 1958-1959. Bank statements with cancelled checks for July-December 1958 and 1959.
    - Checkbook stubs, 1949-1959 (Offsite-box 47)
      There are various gaps in the books. Here are the date ranges and related check number ranges: December 1949 (check #16831)-August 30, 1951 (check #18841); October 23, 1951 (#19094)-January 1954 (#22858); March 11, 1954 (#23116)-May 17, 1954 (#23367); December 30, 1954 (#24125)-May 26, 1955 (#24377); and December 24, 1956 (#26889)-November 20, 1959 (#31925). One of the books still has some blank unused checks in it. The other books only have the check stubs.
  - Subseries III.B. Stock Books and Other Inventories, 1932-1978; 9 Linear feet
    The subseries includes various forms of records reflecting the inventory over time of Robert Ensko Inc. A set of stock books includes a comprehensive view of Ensko's purchases from 1932-1970. The coding in these books likely relate to the codes found in other parts of the collection, including on sales tickets and the stock index cards. There are photographs in the subseries, including small photos in the "stock catalogues" and two albums from the 1960s. And the series includes the extensive sets of index cards used to record inventory at the object level, with purchase and sale information.
    The subseries is arranged by document type.
    - Stock Books, 1932-1970 (Offsite-box 73)
      Includes six volumes that appear to be a complete run from July 1, 1932 to March 31, 1970 of objects purchased by Robert Ensko Inc., source and cost, with other data.
    - Liquidation and Estate Matters, 1970-1978 (Offsite-box 73)
      Includes several auction catalogues from 1970, some clearly related to sales of Robert Ensko Inc. inventory, others perhaps just reference points. Also includes documents from 1978 in connection with the resolution of silver objects in the estate of Dorothea J.W. Ensko (wife of the late Stephen G.C. Ensko).
    - Photograph albums of sterling silver reproductions inventory, 1960s? (Offsite-box 74)
      2 albums of photographs of objects numbered 1-59 with lists of related information. From the list it appears that a third volume is not in the collection.
    - Stock Catalogue of Silver Reproductions, 1958-1967 (Offsite-box 74)
      Includes a set of two books for 1958, revised 1961, and a second set of three books for 1963, revised 1967. Each contain pages with a brief object description, supplier, cost, and sales price. Many pages also include a small photograph. There are also two other similar books, but are undated.
    - Inventory Worksheets, 1954 (Offsite-box 74)
      Includes various worksheets and calculations related to inventory for 1954.
    - Inventory Worksheets, 1948? (Offsite-box 74)
      Includes 5 pads of lists of objects. Mostly undated, but some references to 1948.
    - Index cards: Objects in inventory (Box 1 of 7), 1930s-1940s (Offsite-box 114)
      These seven boxes include sets of index cards related to Ensko's inventory over time. The cards were not reviewed sufficiently during processing to say definitively what their interrelationship is or what the notations all mean. But generally the cards appear to indicate date(s) of acquisition and dates of sale. Some cards have more detail than others. There appear to have been at least 4 numerical sequences/sets of cards over time: one initiated in the early 1930s, a second starting in the mid-1930s and extending to 1954, a third ranging from 1955 to 1967, and a fourth from 1968-1970. But there are other sets of cards related to inventory that are unclear as to how they relate to the others. Also, cards initiated in one year/period may have notations of a different year/period on them.
      This first box holds what appears to be an early set of cards, dating from the early 1930s. The box also holds the beginning of a much larger set of cards that were initiated in the mid-1930s and eventually ended in the mid-1950s; this set continues in the following boxes.
    - Index cards: Objects in inventory (Box 2 of 7), 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 115)
      This box continues the set of cards begun in the 1930s and that extends to 1955.
    - Index cards: Objects in inventory (Box 3 of 7), 1950s (Offsite-box 116)
      This box continues the set of cards begun in the 1930s and extending to the mid 1950s.
    - Index cards: Objects in inventory (Box 4 of 7), 1950s-1960s (Offsite-box 117)
      This box concludes the set of cards begun in the 1930s and ending in 1954. The box also includes the beginning of a new set of cards in 1955 and that extends to the mid-1960s.
    - Index cards: Objects in inventory (Box 5 of 7), 1960s (Offsite-box 118)
      This box continues the set of cards begun in 1955 and that extends to 1967.
    - Index cards: Objects in inventory (Box 6 of 7), 1930s-1970 (Offsite-box 119)
      Ths box concludes the set of cards begun in 1955 and that ends in 1967. The box also holds a relatively small set of cards for the years 1968-1970. And it also holds some miscellaneous sets of stock cards ranging across the decades.
    - Index cards: Objects in inventory (Box 7 of 7), 1930s?-1970 (Offsite-box 120)
      This box holds various miscellaneous sets of inventory cards, some which appear to range to the 1930s. Some cards appear to relate to silver objects owned by the estate of Dorothea Ensko. There are also cards with dealers and other contacts which were found with the stock cards.
  - Subseries III.C. Accounting Records, 1929-1971; 6.83 Linear feet
    The subseries includes various accounting records, especially sales/accounts receivable and inventory purchase/accounts payable records. The subseries also holds some of the earliest records of the firm after its incorporation in 1929, including early tax returns and sales journal. Check registers, payroll records, and other accounting records are in the subseries. None of the journals, ledgers, etc. are complete, though there are substantial periods of time covered by some.
    The subseries is arranged by document type. All are noted in the container list.
    - Sales book, 1929-1932 (Offsite-box 76, Volume 1)
      One volume started in January 1932 and continues through the year. Includes entries showing client name, item purchased, and price, with other data. The volume includes opening entries by customer dating from 1929-1931 that appear to be unsettled purchases as of the journal's start in January 1932.
    - Sales books, 1937-1940 (Offsite-box 76, Volume 2-5)
      4 volumes, one for each year. Includes daily entries showing client name, item purchased, and price, with other data.
    - Repairs and "Wants" book, 1935-1941 (Offsite-box 76, Volume 6)
      One volume. The first 65 pages include a sales record of repairs and engravings by client for 1935. Pages 69-91 include a record by client of their acquisition "wants" (see series IV.A for other "wants" lists from a later period).
    - Ledgers, 1929-1943 (Offsite-box 76, Folder 7-8)
      2 volumes of ledger accounting records: 1929-34, 1935-43.
    - Journal, 1936-1941 (Offsite-box 76, Volume 9)
      One volume of monthly summaries of accounting transactions.
    - Journal, 1955-1958 (Offsite-box 76, Volume 10)
      One small notebook with records of daily sales with client name and price. No object descriptions, but cross-reference to order ticket number.
    - Accounts payable and accounts receivable worksheets, 1938-1953 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 1-17)
      In 10 workbooks and 7 folders of loose sheets. Roughly chronological. Appears to have some gaps, including 1945-46.
    - Accounts payable, circa 1946-1970 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 18)
      Includes a record of Ensko's transactions by dealer. Details only include date of transactions and amount, but provides a broad overview of the scope of business Ensko executed with each dealer over the decades. The bills paid files would provide the object level detail. This volume only appears to include Ensko's transactions with silversmiths and other object dealers, not transactions of a general business nature.
    - Accounts payable registers, 1951-1970 (Offsite-box 77, Folder 19-20)
      Two volumes that record daily transactions with silversmiths and other dealers. Similar in content to the accounts payable volume above, but these volumes are in the form of daily transaction journals rather than organized by dealer account.
    - Accounts receivable/sales books, 1952-1971 (Offsite-box 78, Volume 1-5)
      5 volumes: August 1952-January 1954, January 1954-September 1956, October 1956-November 1959, December 1959-December 1962, then gap, and January 1968-March 1971. The volumes are a running daily list of sales made with client name, order ticket, and cash/receivable data.
    - Petty cash journal, 1946-1955 (Offsite-box 78, Volume 6)
    - Pawnbroker descriptive cards, undated (Offsite-box 78, Folder 7)
      Packet of slips. All are blank forms.
    - Check/transaction register (Box 1 of 2). Flat oversize box, 1953-1961 (Offsite-box 79, Volume 1-3)
      Includes a record of Ensko's check payments in sequence, allocated to expense type. This box holds the first 3 volumes of 5: May 1953-May 1955, June 1955-December 1959, and January 1960-December 1961.
    - Check/transaction register (Box 2 of 2). Flat oversize box, 1962-1968 (Offsite-box 80, Volume 1-2)
      Includes the 4th and 5th of 5 volumes, continued from above: January 1962-December 1963, then gap, January 1966-August 1968.
    - Sales book/tax payments (Box 1 of 2), 1954-1966 (Offsite-box 81)
      Includes worksheets in order ticket sequence (roughly chronological) showing amount of sale and various tax amounts related to it. Please remove the sheets from the box carefully: The sheets are loose in the box, but are in correct order (the pages are numbered 1359-2989).
    - Sales book/tax payments (Box 2 of 2), 1966-1970 (Offsite-box 82, Volume 1)
      One volume continues from above.
    - Various tax filings (2 folders), 1930-1950s (Offsite-box 82, Folder 1-2)
      Robert Ensko Inc was incorporated in 1929 and these files hold the firm's early corporate and other tax returns (1929-1932). Also are various payroll, excise, and other tax filings for the 1950s. For the 1940s, there is only a statement of financial condition for 1948.
    - Various payroll records (4 folders), circa 1947-1957 (Offsite-box 82, Folder 3-6)
      Includes earnings records for various employees for various years and hours and overtime slips.
- Series IV. Client Lists & Related Records, 1937-1970; 12.5 Linear feet
  This series includes records that relate to Ensko's clients as a general matter, including client/customer lists, shipping lists, acknowledgements, client "has and wants" notes, and the like. A significant document type in the series are client files in the form of index cards, ranging from the 1930s-1960s. These cards include records of the clients and their purchases over time, though these are rather summary in form, with more etailed transaction data found in Series V.
  The series is arranged by format.
  - Social Registers, 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 75)
    1967: Social Registers for Baltimore, Boston, Buffalo, Chicago, Cleveland, Cincinnati, Dayton, Philadelphia, Pittsburgh, San Francisco, St. Louis, Washington. 1968: Social Register for New York and the Summer Social Register. 1969: Social Register Locater.
  - Engraving Instructions, circa 1949-1954 (Offsite-box 75)
    Includes a folder of engraving instructions from various clients and one envelope of drawings and other instructions related to engravings for Yale University.
  - Client Lists, 1937-1938, 1960s? (Offsite-box 75)
    Includes two lists: one was found with the 1937-38 correspondence and appears to be the result of an effort to identify "current accounts" and, perhaps, past and potential clients. The other list is undated and unheaded but is likely from the 1960s.
  - Appraisals, circa 1940 (Offsite-box 75)
    Includes the inventory and appraisal for 3 clients: legacy of old English silver given to the Down Town Association by Gherardi Davis (this 2 volume appraisal includes photographs of the objects); C.J Schmidlapp; and silver at Rutgers College Library.
  - Client "Has" and "Wants" Records, 1959-1968 (Offsite-box 75)
    Includes 4 booklets and a set of cards with records by client in terms of what silver they have and what pieces are needed to complete sets. Several of these relate to brides and their weddings. (See series III.C for a volume with a record of "wants" for 1935-41.)
  - Phone/address books, 1960s (Offsite-box 75)
    Two small notebooks with contact information of suppliers.
  - Client order procedure, 1954 (Offsite-box 75)
    This is a 3 page memo, apparently written for a new hire, that includes a detailed description of how order slips should be prepared. This can be useful for understanding the order slips and perhaps the relationship of some of the records in the collection.
  - Shipping lists (Box 1 of 2), 1950-1959, 1961 (Offsite-box 25)
    Daily lists of shipments, showing ticket number, purchaser, shipping address, shipping method. These lists do not include product information. This box includes June 1, 1950 through 1955, missing 1956, then 1957-1959, missing 1960, then 1961.
  - Shipping lists (Box 2 of 2), 1962-1968, 1970 (Offsite-box 24)
  - Customer receipt acknowledgements, 1946, 1955-1966 (Offsite-box 58)
    18 booklets with slips signed by recipients acknowledging receipts of deliveries from Ensko. There is no description of the shipped content, simply acknowledgments of packages received. Mostly 1955-66 with gaps.
  - Index cards: Current clients as of 1960 (Box 1 of 4), 1940s-1960s (Offsite-box 105)
    This box and the next three include index cards with client information, including purchases. According to the labels on the filing cabinets the cards were taken from, the cards represent current clients as of 1960, and the cards reflect updates subsequent to 1960. The cards are in alphabetical order. This box holds clients with names beginning A-EL.
  - Index cards: Current clients as of 1960 (Box 2 of 4), 1940s-1960s (Offsite-box 106)
    Continues from above. This box holds clients with names beginning EM-LIN.
  - Index cards: Current clients as of 1960 (Box 3 of 4), 1940s-1960s (Offsite-box 107)
    Continues from above. This box holds clients with names beginning LIP-SCA.
  - Index cards: Current clients as of 1960 (Box 4 of 4), 1940s-1960s (Offsite-box 108)
    Continues from above. This box holds clients with names beginning SCH-Z.
  - Index cards: Pre-1960 clients (Box 1 of 5), 1930s-1960s (Offsite-box 109)